<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/code/pfs.css"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A Plea for honest dealing against all injustice and injury</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 44KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 18 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2016-02">2016-02 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A55098</idno><idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12375240</idno>
  <idno type="VID">60565</idno>
  <idno type="EEBO-PROQUEST">2248619586</idno>
  
            <idno type="STC">Wing P2509</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R3171</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">12375240</idno>
            <availability><p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above is co-owned by the
    institutions providing financial support to the Early English Books Online Text Creation
    Partnership. This text is available for reuse, according to the terms of <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/"> Creative Commons 0 1.0 Universal
    licence</ref>. The text can be copied, modified, distributed and performed, even for commercial
    purposes, all without asking permission.</p></availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt><relatedItem type="facs" target="https://data.historicaltexts.jisc.ac.uk/view?pubId=eebo-e"/>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A55098)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 60565)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 221:20)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A Plea for honest dealing against all injustice and injury</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 33 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Francis Clark,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1683.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Harvard University Libraries.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Full documentation of the original data capture process is available from the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.
   All versions of the texts are now archived and freely available for download. See <ref target="https://textcreationpartnership.org/faq/#faq05">the TCP Download FAQ</ref>
   for detailed information. The TEI P5 versions are also freely available from the <ref target="https://github.com/textcreationpartnership">TCP Github repository</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp" matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)" replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char" matchPattern="(.+)" replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term type="topical_term">Conduct of life --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term type="topical_term">Justice --  Biblical teaching --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2014-07 </date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images </change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-09 </date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum </label>Sampled and proofread </change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-09 </date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited </change>
         <change>
            <date>2015-03 </date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion </change>
      <change><date>2021-05 </date><label>lb</label>TEI P5 conversion </change></revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:60565:1"/>
            <p>A PLEA FOR Honest Dealing Against all INJUSTICE AND INJURY.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON:</hi> Printed for <hi>Francis Clark,</hi> 1683.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:60565:2"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:60565:2"/>
            <head>A PLEA FOR Honest Dealing, Against all INJUSTICE and INJURY.</head>
            <p>MAN being by his Creation made a Creature of a more dignified and excellent Nature than other Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures; Endowed with that Reason and Understanding with which the other Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, which it pleased the Creator (in sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>serviency to the Humane Nature, and in
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:60565:3"/> order to the manifestation of his own glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry) not in like manner to Endow: having created Man in a similitude to himself, with the very Impression of his Nature, gave him Laws for the Rule of his Pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctice; which said Laws, as respecting Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral Behaviour, are by the Law of Nature imprinted on the Minds of Men, and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>graven with indelible Characters on the Consciences of all Men: insomuch that a most vitiated Practice can hardly blot out, but still remains if not the practice of Justice and Righteousness, yet the secret approbation of it even in the minds of the most corrupted Men; yea, our Nature would be the greatest enducement to all fair, just and honest dealing, if we did not stifle and smother the Dictates thereof, though we, through the depravity of our nature, are fallen from our chiefest good, yet if we suppress not even our own Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, there yet remains the legible Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racters of Justice and honest dealing written thereon, and unless we would wilfully raze them out for the sake of our impious Lusts and Passions, they will plainly remain.</p>
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:60565:3"/>
            <p>But not only the light of Nature, but also the light of the written Law of God, evinceth that Men ought to do Justice and Right, and that by Injury and Oppression, Persons, Families, Nations, become mise<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable and desolate; yea, that it is incon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sistent with the Nature, with Piety, with Humanity, the proof whereof is apparent in the following <hi>Sections.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="1">§. 1. Against doing Injustice, or Oppres<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sing our Neighbours, we have an eminent Pattern even from the spotless Lives of the <hi>Heathens,</hi> with respect to Moral Honesty, which said Virtue did with most splendid Magnificence shine forth in several of them who had no greater discoveries than what were afforded by the light of nature, yet how did that great Law of nature rule in their Hearts, not to wrong their <hi>Neighbours,</hi> but to deal justly with one another: <hi>Christianity</hi> doth not only instruct us in this Lesson, but <hi>Nature</hi> too: doing justly and honestly is not good with respect to the future World only, but likewise for the present: it is the best way of
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:60565:4"/> living, now since the <hi>Heathens,</hi> who were only guided by the Principles of Nature, who had not those Divine Revelations we have, have been so remarkable in their Morals; let them not shame us Christians, as if Christianity licens'd Men to be inju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious and oppressing: and let us take heed that they do not rise up against us, and condemn us another Day.</p>
            <p n="2">§. 2. For Men to do Injustice or Op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>press their <hi>Neighbour,</hi> or do any other Injury, is against the Law of nature, which flows forth to the Sons of Men from the eternal Law of God, the Law of nature being a copying out of the eternal Law, and the imprinting it upon the Breast of a rational Being; that eternal Law was as in a manner incarnated in the Law of nature: so that the Law of nature doth strictly oblige and tye us to the due obser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vance thereof, as it immediately flows from the eternal Law of God, and thereby has the right of primogeniture of all Laws: and all the good and wholsom Laws in the World are but <hi>Idea's</hi> and Representations
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:60565:4"/> of it, and concur with that Law of nature, it is essential to a rational Creature, who being endowed with reason and under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>standing, he it is suitable and connatural to it to be regulated by a Law: Man being made a free Agent and qualified with ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tional Faculties, and thereby rendred capable of a Law, and suitable unto it; when therefore he breaks this Law of na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, by injuring others, Oh how doth he even strike at his own Being! How doth he offer violence to his own Nature! How doth he endeavour to blot out those inde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lible Characters of Justice and Honesty which are imprinted in the Humane na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture!</p>
            <p n="3">§. 3. Injuring and oppressing Men doth unavoidably retort guilt upon the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sciences of the injurious; Conscience is the natural Pulse of the Soul, and the impar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tial Judge of Men's Actions, it is a close Companion, it is an inward Light which will discover a Man to himself: the <hi>Apostle</hi> in <hi>Rom.</hi> 2.14, 15. felt the <hi>Heathen</hi> Pulse thus beating, it sometimes accusing, and sometimes
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:60565:5"/> excusing them; Humane Laws bind Men to do justly, but if they do not, this is a Divine Serjeant that will arrest the person offending; if Men do not justly, it will not act flatteringly, for it's God's Vice-Gerent in the Soul of a Man: thus it arrested <hi>Cain,</hi> and threw him in the Prison of Trouble and Confusion, for the Blood of his righteous Brother <hi>Abel;</hi> thus also <hi>Lamech;</hi> and of all Troubles it is most intolerable, for says the Wise Man, <hi>A wounded Spirit, who can bear!</hi> It molests the most inward Faculties, and haunteth the secret Cogitations, filling the Mind with Fear and Confusion, <hi>as Cain I shall be a Vagabond, and whosoever meeteth me, will slay me.</hi> Let us therefore, as we would avoid an accusing, troubling and torment<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Conscience, avoid injuring and wrong<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing any Men, for Conscience will prosecute us, for breaking the Law of God and Nature.</p>
            <p n="4">§. 4. To injure, wrong, or oppress Men, renders them incapable of that calmness, quietude, and peaceableness, which is
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:60565:5"/> implied in the light of Nature and right reason, if men were more tun'd and regu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lated by reason, there would be more har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony in the World, and not that dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cord that is too common therein. Man by Nature is a sociable Creature, and this light of Reason is a sociable light, this <hi>Can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dle of the Lord</hi> would give forth its light purely and clearly, if mens interests and passions did not almost extinguish it.</p>
            <p n="5">§. 5. To injure and wrong others, as it renders men incapable of the quietude which is implied in the Light of Nature, it also puts out the pleasant <hi>light</hi> of our own <hi>Reason,</hi> it is to cast away from our selves the good he has given us, <hi>All Light is pleasant;</hi> yea, it is even the very smile of <hi>Nature,</hi> and the varnish of the Creation. Oh how pleasant is it to behold the Lamp of <hi>Reason!</hi> how pleasant to behold an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tellectual <hi>Sun!</hi> it is a pleasure that respects the <hi>Soul</hi> of man, and so it is of a far higher and more noble extract than all the plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sures of sence. But oh how dolorous is it when extinguish'd and aim'd to be wronged
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:60565:6"/> and undone by our injustice and oppres<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sion.</p>
            <p n="6">§. 6. To act injuriously to others is even against the Documents of the Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thens, not only in so doing, do <hi>we</hi> fall short of their <hi>Examples,</hi> but also of their <hi>Documents,</hi> as <hi>Socrates, Diogenes, Aristotle, Plato,</hi> and many others: Now if <hi>these</hi> by the <hi>Light of Nature</hi> attained to great <hi>Mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sures</hi> of <hi>Moral behaviour,</hi> if they <hi>walked, lived,</hi> and have left behind them <hi>Documents</hi> for <hi>honest living;</hi> if we fall short of them, though <hi>We are professed Christians,</hi> if yet we are so far from regarding the Les<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son of Justice and Honesty, as commanded in the <hi>Word of God,</hi> and also as pressed up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on us even by <hi>Heathens</hi> themselves, of what sore <hi>Condemnation</hi> shall we be thought worthy?</p>
            <p n="7">§. 7. To injure and wrong others, is to walk contrary to the <hi>light of our Reason,</hi> which is a <hi>light for the feet, and a Lant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>horn for the Paths,</hi> which is the leading and <hi>guiding</hi> power of the Soul, <hi>Reason</hi> is
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:60565:6"/> that which carries a <hi>Torch</hi> before the <hi>Will,</hi> and also it is an <hi>Eye</hi> for the <hi>blind,</hi> for else in vain would it be to <hi>light up a Candle</hi> for a <hi>blind faculty</hi> to see withal; now for men to abuse this <hi>Gift</hi> of God, to abuse the light of <hi>Reason,</hi> to sin against their Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sciences and knowledge, is without <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance,</hi> the way to inevitable Ruin.</p>
            <p n="8">§. 8. To injure or wrong others, as it is contrary to the <hi>Law of Nature,</hi> and <hi>Right Reason:</hi> so also to the revealed Law of God in the <hi>Scriptures,</hi> which is suffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ently to be proved therefrom, 1 <hi>Thess.</hi> 4.6. <hi>That no man go beyond and defraud his bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in any matter, because the Lord is the avenger of all such.</hi> If we are <hi>Christians</hi> we must submit unto the Rule of that <hi>Word of God</hi> we pretend to believe or cease to profess <hi>Christianity;</hi> for if we must needs make the World believe that we serve God, and trust in him, when our practice loudly proclaimes <hi>Defiance</hi> to him by <hi>breach</hi> of <hi>his Commandments,</hi> though we may <hi>make our boast of the Law, yet by breaking the law, do we dishonour God.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="9">
               <pb n="10" facs="tcp:60565:7"/>§. 9. To injure and wrong others is a crime of a most hainous and dreadful na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture and consideration in that it brings the vindictive Righteousness of <hi>God</hi> upon us in this <hi>World</hi> as well as in another, even Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture and nature it self will require us to look for the same Measure from <hi>God</hi> and men, either in this <hi>World</hi> or the other, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with we mete unto others; He that pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pares ruin for another must reasonably ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pect to partake of destruction himself, a guilty conscience must need haunt the inju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious by suggesting to them the Expectation of suffering worse things themselves than they impose upon their Neighbours, and so indeed one under, such a Character may rightly fear, for it is the peculiar attribute of <hi>Almighty God,</hi> the <hi>Lord is the avenger of all such,</hi> and <hi>vengance is mine,</hi> and the <hi>God to whom vengance belongeth,</hi> and <hi>He will re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pay it,</hi> hence how promptly did the consci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Minds of <hi>Josephs</hi> Brethren acquit <hi>God</hi> for a Just retribution upon themselves, in revenging their carriage towards their Bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther when they said, <hi>We are verily guilty,
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:60565:7"/> concerning our Brother, in that we saw the anguish of his Soul, when he besought us and we would not hear: therefore is this distress come upon us;</hi> in like Manner also did the Conscience of <hi>Adonibezeck</hi> recoil upon him, when his Thumbs and great Toes were cut of, <hi>Seventy Kings</hi> saith he, <hi>having their Thumbs and great Toes cut off, gathered their Meat under my table as I have done, so mod hath requited me.</hi> Instances of this nature which stand register'd in Scripture for our Ensample are various: let us consider the Wo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s which are in Scripture denounced a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst the injurious, and <hi>fear and not do so wickedly! He made a Pit, and digged it, Saith the Psalmist</hi> in they 7th Psalm, where speaking of the wicked man <hi>(and is falen in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the Ditch which he made; his mischief sha- return upon his own Head, and his violent dealing shall come down upon his own Pate;)</hi> And if the injurious and wrongers of others would know what They must expect, let them hear what the Wiseman saith in <hi>Prov.</hi> 1.21. <hi>They shall eat of the Fruit of their own way, and be filled with their own devices,</hi> and again in the 5th Chapter, <hi>His own ini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quitie
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:60565:8"/> shall take the wicked Himself, and he shall be holden with the cords of his Sins,)</hi> Let also the injurious consider the Prophet <hi>Isaiahs</hi> Wo, <hi>viz,</hi>
               <q>Wo to thee that spoilest, and thou wast not spoiled; and dealest Treacherously, and they dealt not Treach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erously with thee: when thou shalt cease to spoil, thou shalt be spoiled; and when thou shalt make an end to deal Treacher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ously, They shall deal Treacherously with thee.</q> Nay most formidable is the threatning in <hi>Micah</hi> viz, <q>Then shall they cry unto the Lord, but he will not hear them; He will even hide his Face from them at that time, as they have behaved themselves ill in their doings.</q> Yea Further let us remark that most observable passage of our blessed Saviour; <q>With what Measure you mete, it shall be Measured to you again.</q> But in short let that general Exhortation of St. <hi>Paul</hi> to the <hi>Galatians,</hi> be considered <hi>viz.</hi>
               <q>Be not deceived, God is not mocked; for whatsoever a Man soweth, that shall he also reap.</q> It is a common Proverb <hi>Prout Sementem Feceris, ita &amp; Metes:</hi> as you sow you shall reap, They that plow iniquity
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:60565:8"/> and wickedness, reap the same, But to him that soweth righteousness shall be a sure reward; He that acteth unjustly to man shall find severe Justice from <hi>God,</hi> He that ruineth his Neighbour shall find ruin for his portion, He that oppresseth o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers has no warrant to believe but that he shall come to confusion himself, for saith the Scripture, <hi>He shall have Judgment without Mercy that hath shewed no Mercy;</hi> What Mercy find we in the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable of <hi>Dives</hi> and <hi>Lazarus</hi> had <hi>Dives</hi> for his Cruelty, and injustice to poor <hi>Lazarus,</hi> for it is a breach of Justice when <hi>God</hi> hath given a man riches and wealth for that man to shew no Mercy to the poor and needy, how then by injustice do we prepare Scourges for our selves and pull di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine vengance in both <hi>Worlds</hi> upon our own Pates? For since <hi>God</hi> is a <hi>God</hi> of Righteousness and his Justice is his essential attribute, how can we think, but that the <hi>Judge of the whole Earth will do right;</hi> and if men will break through all the bonds of Equity and Justice to wrong others, and to di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vest them of their due right, how can it be ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pected but that <hi>God</hi> will <hi>plead the cause of the op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pressed, and return the violence of the oppressor up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on his own head.</hi> Nay this sin of injustice is so displeasing to <hi>God,</hi> that often it brings Plagues and Miseryes upon a Community, and is attend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with national ruin, and even seldom in this <hi>World</hi> passes without the signal tokens of Divine vengance and displeasure.</p>
            <p n="10">§. 10. To injure and wrong others, doth most
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:60565:9"/> wretchedly displease and reject that great Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandment <hi>viz,</hi> to love our Neighbour as our self. We suppose hereby that every man has an entire love and regard to himself, the obligation of loving his Neighbour is here grounded on love to himself, and from this Principle of self-love is it that a man is desirous not to receive wrong from others, but to desire right; here therefore it is made the pattern and Measure of his demean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our towards others. We certainly need not a pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept to injoyn upon us the love of our selves, since it is a principle which nature teaches, this appears even from that instinct of nature which we find to be in sensitive as well as rational creatures, <hi>viz</hi> that self-love or desire of their own preservation and good, and thereupon an inclination and ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petite towards what is good, suitable and conve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nient with their nature, attended with an aver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sation and declining what is otherwise. We read in holy writ that no man ever hated his own flesh, but nourisheth and cheriseth it: No man in his right wits, no man unless he were mad and alie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nated and estranged from himself, but would em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brace the common principles of self-love. But what a sad consideration is it whereas man is by the obligation of the principles of nature engaged to self-love, yet how generally do we see men e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven forgo those very principles and forsake that very instinct of nature (even to the denying of that nature wherewith <hi>God</hi> hath invested them, and to the disgrace of the principles of that nature wherewith they are endowed) which nature as
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:60565:9"/> humane imports humanity; and how is it possible to believe that there is humanity if any man hates and injures his Neighbours; what is more contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dictory to the rules and Impressions of reason on the faculties of reasonable Souls? Nay what can we say of injurious persons but that they are E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemies to nature, that they forsake the princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples of Reason, and offer violence to themselves, and renounce the commands of God, and extin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guish (as much as they can) the Light of nature, and must reasonably expect that Just doom that is thundred forth in the menaces of Scripture a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst such.</p>
            <p n="11">§. 11. Men ought by no means to wrong or in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jure others, for we were all out of the same stock, and equal by nature, though as to our states and conditions therein there is a disparity, yet it is no otherwise than Figures of the same denomination set in different places: one is a unit, another a ten, another an hundred: We are all of us, whether High or Low, yet descended from one Common Parent: We are of the same Mould, and were all derived from the Dust, and shall return unto the same again; We all owe our being and original to the <hi>God</hi> of us all; in him the Poor man as well as the rich doth <hi>live and move, and hath his being;</hi> hence may rationally be inferred that since we are thus equal by nature, and received our being from <hi>God,</hi> and Preservation of that being is dayly given us of <hi>God,</hi> then <hi>Mal.</hi> 2.10. saith the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet, <hi>Have we not all one Father? Hath not one
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:60565:10"/> God created us? Why do we deal Treacherously e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very man against his Brother?</hi> It is altogether un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>accountable for any man to wrong another, and appears greatly evil and base by reason of that consanguinity of nature whereby all men are link<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked together in the relation they stand each to o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther as fellow creatures; as being created by the same <hi>God,</hi> and as fellow Brethren being prefer'd and maintained by the same paternal care and protection. This very consideration had so great an influence upon <hi>Job,</hi> that in his afflictions, We may see his appeal from having committed injury or injustice when he said, <hi>If I did despise the cause of my Man-servant, or of my Maid-servant, when they contended with me, what then shall I do when God riseth up? And when he visiteth, what shall I answer him? Did not he that made me in the womb make him? And did not one fashion us in the womb?</hi> We are made by the same <hi>God</hi> but not to undo and wrong one another: pathetick to this purpose is that of <hi>Paul</hi> in the <hi>Acts; God that made the World, and all things therein, hath made of one blood all Nations of men for to dwell on the face of the Earth, there is then very great reason that we should so carry our selves towards others, ss we would desire from them,</hi> in as much as we are all partakers of the same nature, joynt possessors of the same Earth, branches sprouting out from one and the same stock: We see it plainly in Lions, Wolves, Bears and the most ravenous and sterce Bruits, this instinct of nature, <hi>viz,</hi> that they devour not one another, for we see every Beast loveth his
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:60565:10"/> like and not devour Creatures of the same kind with themselves, therefore if not from a more rational ground and more noble and excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent Principles men forbear not to injure and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour one another, yet let this Example of that in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stinct of nature which is even in brutes prevail up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on men not to act that which is worse than bruitish; for if those Savage creatures to which every one is Obnoxious to danger and destruction if catched in their reach and power, yet agree with each o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther: then Man whose nature is excelling, should if from no other tye and obligation, not devour and wrong his fellow creature, still should even the communion and Participation of the same Nature be sufficient, since it is so in the very Savage brutes. And if any man wrong and injure others they may justly be divested of the title of Humane and just<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly called Diabolical and worse than Bruitish.</p>
            <p n="12">§. 12. Let any injurious oppressing man con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sider, That it is very possible he may be in the same Case with the person whom he so injureth and abuseth: it may very probably be his own state and fate. Suitable to this is the passage of Holy writ in <hi>Isaiah,</hi> where the Prophet saith, <hi>As with the People, so with the Priest, or Prince; as with the Servant, so with his Master; as with the Maid, so with her Mistress; as with the Buyer, so with the Seller; as with the Lender, so with the Bor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rower; as with the taker of Ʋsury, so with the Giver of Ʋsury to him;</hi> That which happens to one may happen to another, for as we are Men We are partakers together of the same Nature,
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:60565:11"/> We are incient to the same fate with others; and though one be lifted up and prosperous, he may nevertheless become dejected and distressed, <hi>There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore let him that thinketh he standeth</hi> (as saith the Apostle) <hi>take heed lest he fall,</hi> and not say with vain confidence <hi>that in his Prosperity he shall never be moved,</hi> which though uttered by holy man, yet it was in repentance for that his vain and mistaken confidence, therefore excellent is the exhortation of the Author to the <hi>Hebrews, Remember</hi> (saith he) <hi>Them that are in bonds, as bound with them; and them which suffer adversity; as being your selves also in the body;</hi> Whilst we are in the bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy we lye Obnoxious to the same afflictions with others, and though We may not yet feel them, yet we have not the least assurance that we shall not, but if we be the occasion of afflictions and sorrow to others by injury and oppression, let us Remember and take this for a warning piece that we are all exposed to Variety of Changes in the <hi>World,</hi> and may likely Exchange our state and condition with other men, and therefore if we would not be oppress'd and injured; we should forbear it to others, and follow that Spirit of Sym<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pathy and Compassion to which the Apostle Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>horteth the <hi>Romans, Rejoyce therefore with them that Rejoyce, and Weep with them that Weep;</hi> Which is a natural Principle of Sympathy and Compassion with others, we being clothed with the same flesh and frailty and so liable to the same affliction and adversity with others.</p>
            <p n="13">
               <pb n="19" facs="tcp:60565:11"/>§. 13. Let us not injure, wrong or oppress o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers in any Manner, in consideration of our Savi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ours Golden Rule of all morality and just and honest dealing, when he said, <hi>Whatsoever ye would that Men should do unto you, do unto them likewise, this is the Law and the Prophets;</hi> this Rule of hone<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sty and justice is that which the Law and Prophets greatly call for, it is a fruitful Epitome of divers precepts delivered in the Law and the Prophets: Now <hi>we have</hi> Moses <hi>and the Prophets, and if we will not here them,</hi> let us expect <hi>Dives</hi> doom and fate, let the injurers oppessours of their Neighbours ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pect that place of Torment as a due recompence of their injustice.</p>
            <p>It was one end of our Saviours comming into the <hi>World,</hi> to fullfil the Law, he came not to a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brogate or take away the binding Power and Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority of the Law and Prophets, but to fullfil their Prescription and Rules, so that he establisheth his precepts by them, for saith he, <q>Think not, that I am come to destroy the Law or the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets; I am not come to destroy, but to full<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fil:</q> Now the Moral Law or the Law prescribing rules for Just and Honest living, and righteous deal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing between Man and Man, is but a revival of the Law of Nature, which said law of nature depends on eternal and never failing principles and rules of Equity and Justice; and this our Saviour was so far from rendring null and void as that he has ratifyed it, the Laws and Prophets being as au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thentick as ever, and do strictly oblige us to those Laws, which are built on eternal principles of E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quity,
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:60565:12"/> and so do as virtually oblige us as ever they did the <hi>Jews,</hi> though those Laws which respect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed their polity in Church and state, as they only respected time and place, and a certain People had a binding power and no further, unless deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mined according to those mutable Circumstances, but the moral law of Justice and Equity is ever ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liging, not only from the light of nature but di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine Revelation, as in the forecited phrase of our Blessed Saviour, and in his reference to the <hi>Law and the Prophets.</hi> And in Scripture we find <hi>Abra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham</hi> preferring the voice of <hi>Moses and the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets,</hi> even <hi>before one rising from the Dead,</hi> for the warning of the Living, <hi>If they hear not</hi> Moses <hi>and the Prophets, neither will they be perswaded though one rose from the Dead;</hi> if we will have no respect for the Law and the Prophets, we are Atheists, if we will pretend to reverence those ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly writings, and yet practice Oppression and injury to our Neighbours we are perfect Hypocrites, and what is the portion of the Hypocrite <hi>but weeping and wailing and gnashing of teeth?</hi> Our blessed Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour when he urgeth this Golden Rule, he backs it with divine Authority and infallible power, <hi>viz.</hi> the Scriptures which are the <hi>Law and the Prophets,</hi> which bind us to obedience thereof, as they are the peremptory Commands and injunctions of our Creatour, and the Rule of our Faith and man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners, which if we reject, <hi>We reject the Councel of God against our selves,</hi> and without repentance shall suffer the revenging wrath of God for ever for con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt of and disobedience unto his Command<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments.</p>
            <p n="14">
               <pb n="21" facs="tcp:60565:12"/>§. 14. By acting injustice and oppression a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst others, we do most injury, and hurt to our selves; injustice is a kind of intestine, civil sedition and War in the Soul, causing an unjust oppressour to fight against himself, in Troubling, Vexing and Tormenting himself. An Heathen writer endeavour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to confute this assertion, saying, <hi>It is impossible for a man to do injury to himself, for</hi> (saith he) <hi>all injury must be acted against another;</hi> but the same Author forgetting that argument at the latter end of his Book, asserted <q>Whoever doth wrong or injustice to another, wrongeth himself, and in offering injury to another doth himself wrong, in that he is the cause why himself transgresseth the Laws.</q> The very Law of nature will de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clare him who wrongeth the dictates thereof to be the cause of his own evil, and wrong his own nature, but he who injureth his Neighbour wrongs the very dictates of nature; he therefore who causeth himself to act injuriously transgresseth the Law of his own nature, and whosoever doth of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer violence to his own nature, can by no means be otherwise than an enemy to himself.</p>
            <p n="15">§. 15. To do injustice and injury is contrary to the Divine president in Scripture of Gods <hi>Judicial</hi> wayes of proceeding, though <hi>Sodoms</hi> sins were sins of the deepest stain; though their pollutions were the most obscence and filthy which ever were com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted by a rebellious and wicked People, yet when <hi>God</hi> intended to proceed against them in a <hi>Judicial</hi> way, how doth he comply with the <hi>Law of nature;</hi> he would neither condemn nor exeute
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:60565:13"/> before he had not only cleared his Justice in him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>self, or to his <hi>Angels;</hi> but also to <hi>Abraham, Lot</hi> and other spectatours, that he might be <hi>Justifyed in his dealings, and clear when he Judgeth;</hi> he would and did, go down to hear and see, in or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der to a <hi>Judicial</hi> proceeding against them. Now if God would not proceed against a wicked abo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minable <hi>Sodom,</hi> but clear his Justice and infi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitely condescend thus to put his actions on mans Judgment, thus strictly to observe the Law of nature; Oh how greatly do these demerit the di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine vengance without any mixture of Mercy, which arbitrarily refuse to obey all rule of Equity and Justice, to be regulated by no Laws nor injun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions of Right, that say <hi>Stat pro ratione voluntas</hi> or rather <hi>voluptas.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="16">§. 16. To do injustice and wrong to others ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders those persons most like and conformable to the Image of the Devil, <hi>Who goeth about like a roaring Lyon seeking whom he may devour;</hi> injuri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous persons have the very Idea and impression of the diabolical nature, how very Suitable are their natures which consist in devouring others, saith our blessed Saviour to the Malignant <hi>Jews, Ye are of your Father the Devil, and the lusts of your Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ye will do, he was a Lyar from the beginning,</hi> he was a defrauder, beguiler, and an injurious one, he at first wronged man of his innocence, he be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiled man of his felicity, and he injureth him of his Salvation, he is the Father of lyes, and fraud, beguiling, and injury; and those who are in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jurious
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:60565:13"/> to others, are not exempted from being Children of the <hi>Devil,</hi> for they bear the similitude of the diabolical nature; and it may be as truly said of them, as it was of Old, <hi>Adam, He Begat a Son in his own likeness.</hi> So the Devil hath these Children in his own likeness, these are his first born, these are the very heirs of darkness, these will be the hottest Firebrands of Hell without re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance; these are the Devils Drudges, full fraught with <hi>Malice, Malignity, Envy, Hatred,</hi> and all the <hi>unfruitful works of Darkness;</hi> for whom is, with the fallen Angels, <hi>reserved the blackness of darkness for ever.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="17">§. 17. For men to act injuriously or oppressing<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, is the certain way to bring ruin on their Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>milyes, and on the Nation wherein they dwell; for as the posterity of the righteous shall be blest, so likewise the posterity of the unrighteous blasted or cursed the <hi>Righteous God judgeth righteously;</hi> It must not be supposed that God will shew his revenging wrath in a future World, on the poste<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity of unrighteous parents; for that is contradict<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in the holy Scriptures, in disowning that <hi>Adagy</hi> of old, <hi>The Fathers have eaten Sower Grapes, and the Childrens Teeth are set on Edge.</hi> No, not so, <hi>The soul that sinneth it shall dye.</hi> As <hi>Job</hi> or <hi>Daniel</hi> cannot by their Righteousness save Son or Daughter, so unrighteous parents cannot by their unrighteousness destroy Son or Daughter; for if the Son seeth the unrighteousness of the Father, and considereth of his Fathers wayes, and turneth
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:60565:14"/> his feet from his Fathers violent dealing, it is no o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwise then consistent with the Divine Judgment and mercy to save such a Son alive, tho the Father dye, that is, the Second death; but this respects ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther world. In this world it's frequently nay most commonly otherwise, for God herein <hi>Visiteth the Iniquity of the Fathers upon their Children to the third and fourth Generation;</hi> That has respect to this World, for though God threatned to cut off even him that Pisseth against the Wall of <hi>Ahabs</hi> house, yet none can suppose this cutting off to im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port more then an infliction of temporal punish<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment on such a person, the more perspicuously thereby to manifest Gods wrath against <hi>Ahab,</hi> and the glorious declaration of Gods vindictive Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stice against such like Rebels, against the Majestie of Heaven: for God doth so clear his Justice and Righteousness oft in the sight of Men in not suffer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing even the off-spring of unrighteousness and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jurious persons to pass without the effect of vin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dictive Justice; But oh to what ruin and desolati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on doth injury and oppression bring a Nation! Sin brings a People and family low; Sin doth tend to the overthrow and ruin of States and Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments; Sin is the very shame of a People and Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion; Sin brings down Gods Judgments upon a Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion; God punisheth Lands for the Sins of the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>habitants thereof.</p>
            <p n="18">§. 18. By acting injuriously and unrighteously, what an intolerable shame are persons so acting to Christianity, seeing they profess themselves pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selytes
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:60565:14"/> thereunto, which if they do, let them consi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the reproach they bring upon Christianity. Since Christians are by the precepts of their Master enjoyn'd to higher duties of Charity: but by in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>justice and oppression, do instead of living in the practice of them, absolutely unlearn even those common rules of Justice which nature it self in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>structs us in. St. <hi>Paul</hi> reproves those of the <hi>Circumcision</hi> very aptly on this occasion, when he said that <hi>The name of God was Blasphemed among the Gentiles,</hi> for there was a great unagreeable<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness between their practice and their Law: the Law under which they lived was straight and good, but their practices were loose and bad. But alas, how is the name of God still blasphemed by oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>casion of the evil and licentious practices of con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verted <hi>Gentiles;</hi> how do the <hi>Turks</hi> and <hi>Insid<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ls</hi> speak evil of Christianity for the sake of the evil practices of the professors thereof? Therefore ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther let Christians walk according to the rules of Justice and Right, or else cease to be called by that most Excellent name; let them endeavour to wipe off the Scandal and reproach which Injustice has brought by their means upon Christianity it self, which is purely immaculate, and a law of the strictest Justice and integrity.</p>
            <p n="19">§. 19. For men to act injuriously or wish op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pression against others, is bare-faced Robbery and against the common good of mankind. And this may be done several wayes, as by Power and Vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence, by which many Nations and Princes have
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:60565:15"/> been turned out of their Rights, and also many private men out of their Estates, and in their room have come Tyrants, Thiefs and Robbers: So if a man covets his Neighbours Lands or Goods, he pretends a claim to them, and then Endeavours to corrupt Justice by Bribes and Gift, or else o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver-ruling it by greatness and Authority, gets Judgment on his side: this is indeed an high op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pression, and of the most black and dreadful sort, thus to make the Law, which is intended for the Protection and defence of men Rights, to be the means of Subverting and Destroying them; and it is a very heavy Guilton every one that is concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in such an act of Injustice, and sometimes the ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry Necessities of the Oppress'd are a means of his Oppression: thus it falls out in the case of Extor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and griping usury: for a poor man to be in Extream want of Mony, and then for the Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tortioner to take occasion inhumanly to Gripe and unconscionably to Exort, is most Barbarous Rob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bery and Injustice; and by how much more helpless the afflicted and oppressed Person is, by so much the more is the Guilt of the Oppressour increas<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed.</p>
            <p>And to conclude, Oppression and Injustice is indeed a most Crying Guilt, it Cryes up to Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven for Vengance; and the Cry thereof goeth into the hearing and Cognizance of Omnipotent pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er: And though God may seem to have Leaden Feet in the retribution of his Justice, yet Oppres<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sors
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:60565:15"/> shall certainly find that he hath Iron Hands. Let them be assur'd of it from <hi>Ezek.</hi> 18.12. <hi>He that hath oppressed the Poor, and hath spoiled by Violence, He shall surely dye, his blood shall be upon Him:</hi> God hath so engag<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>d himself a Patron for the Poor and oppressed, that he is in honour (as it were oblig'd) to defend them, and to judge their cause, and to avenge them, against all their unjust oppressours. We may clearly see God most Eminently engaging himsef for them in <hi>Psalm.</hi> 12.5. <hi>For the Oppression of the Poor, for the Sighing of the Needy, now will I arise saith the Lord, I will set him in safety from him that puffeth at him.</hi> The Op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pressour is not like t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> get much by engag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing himself against God. Therefore let us follow the good and wholsome Advice of the Wise Man, <hi>viz, Rob not the Poor be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cause He is Poor, neither oppress the afflicted in the Gate, for the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ord will plead their Cause, and will spoil the Soul of those that spoileth them.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Wherefore seeing injustice and oppression are Sins of so high a Nature, and attend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with so dismal and grievous consequences
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:60565:16"/> and effects, let us loath Injustice and live in the practice of Justice and Righteousness, for that will bring us comfort and Blessed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness in the Latter end.</p>
            <p>Let us endeavour after Negative Justice, which consisteth in doing no wrong or in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jury to any. A man is in several respects liable to receive injury: He may be injured in his Soul, in his Body, or in his Estate, or in his Credit, therefore Negative Justice lays a restriction upon us in respect of all these.</p>
            <p>In respect of the Soul we must not act un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>justly against the Soul of any Man, the Soul is the Essential part of Man, the Soul is the breath of God in Man, it is the most noble and excellent part. When we entice Men to sin, when we impose our own lusts and impieties upon them, then is the Soul wrong<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, and surely there can not be a greater wrong then to bring this great evil upon the Soul, for sin is the Disease and wound of the Soul, because it is contrary to the health and prosperity of it, which lyes in Grace, because it makes God desirable to our Souls, and our Souls acceptable to
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:60565:16"/> God. Now thus do we wound and Mace<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate the Souls of Men, when we draw them to Sin.</p>
            <p>As we must not act injuriously against the Souls of any, so neither against their Bodyes, for God doth strictly prohibit this in the Moral Law, when he said, <hi>Thou shalt do no Murder:</hi> But of Murder there are se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral degrees, as false accusation, also by Endeavouring to make a man Drunk; where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by he may have some Mischief done him, this is Murther; So is Anger, Hatred and Uncharitableness, as the Apostle saith, <hi>He that loveth not his Brother is a Murtherer,</hi> Now to act injustice against a Mans Body, is some degree of Murther, therefore let us not act unjustly against the Bodyes of our Neighbours, for the Scripture saith, <hi>No Murtherer shall inherit the Kingdom of God.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And as we must n<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>t act injuriously against the Bodyes of any Men, so neither against their estates, for this is the express sence of the tenth Commandment, <hi>Thou shalt not Covet his Neighbours House, Nor his Wife, nor his Ox, nor his Ass, nor any thing that is his.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="30" facs="tcp:60565:17"/>
            <p>And as we must not act injuriously a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst Mens Estates, so neither must we by any means impair their Credit; for a <hi>Good name is better then precious oyntment,</hi> a good name is a tender thing in the eyes of a Man that enjoys it; if by Back-biting and slander another takes it away, the person from whom it is taken may be injur'd even of his lively-hood in the World: therefore have our Laws for the good of mutual So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciety and common Security, in this Case, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vided remedies, for Persons thus injur'd, by Actions, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Let us endeavour after Positive Justice as well as after Negative, which Positive Justice is a yielding or giving to every Man that which by Right, and in point of Justice, he can challenge or demand of us; of these dues there are some general to all mankind, and others restrain'd to some Men of grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter Condition and Quality, which becomes due to them by Virtue of such Qualificati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons. Sincerity of intention and mind is due to all mankind, even, as from the Lowest to the Highest, so from the highest to the lowest. A double mind is Odious to God
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:60565:17"/> and hateful to Men, <hi>Speaking of lyes in hy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pocrisy</hi> is that which God abominates, and is not either pleasing to or safe for Man: even the most treacherous Villain esteemeth an upright Man, and though through an evil mind he will not act justly to o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>hers: yet he would not that any should act un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>justly towards him.</p>
            <p>Meekness and Gentleness is a Common debt we owe to mankind, not to be of so sullen and Churlish a Temper as we find in holy writ <hi>Nabal</hi> was of, 1 <hi>Sam</hi> 25.17. Who was of such a base Temper <hi>that a Man could not speak to Him</hi> The pride of Mans Nature is the greatest impediment to this Virtue; but let Proud High Morose Men Remember the words of our blessed Saviour; <hi>He that exalteth Himself shall be abased, and He that humbleth himself shall be exalted.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>There is a respect and honour due to Men in regard of their Rank and Quality; <hi>So Honour to whom Honour, Fear to whom Fear,</hi> as saith the <hi>Apostle.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>To the Poor though there is not that due srepect and honour which is to our betters,
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:60565:18"/> yet there is due an humbleness of mind, a condescention, a pity; yea, nature instructs us, in that they are of the same mould with others, they should have Natural Pity, <hi>Prov.</hi> 3.27. <hi>With-hold not good from him to whom it is due, when it is in the power of thine hand to do it; and say not to thy Neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour, go and come again, and to Morrow I will give, when thou hast it by thee.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>We are also by positive Justice obliged to Gratitude: Ingratiude is an unnatural kind of bestialty; A man must divest him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>self of humane Nature if he can not have a kind resentment of his benefactours boun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty; which even the Publicans and Sinners (as saith our Saviour) did observe, when they do good to those that do good to them.</p>
            <p>Many are the dutyes which are enjoyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed us by virtue of positive Justice towards our Neighbours, towards our Relations, towards our Magistrates; in respect of the whole course of our Life, but the sum of all which our Saviour calleth the Law and the Prophets, is, that we should do to men as we would that they should do to us;
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:60565:18"/> which is the true standard of Justice and Equity, and the unerring rule of all Right; which that we may walk according to that Rule, and that Peace may be upon us, let us also in Charity to others which may not follow this Rule, Pray with our Church, That it may please thee to bring into the way of Truth, all such as have erred and are deceived.</p>
            <trailer>THE END.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>